A lot of people want to launch a premium
product and I'm like no. I think that's
a the status quo. It's like no, but
prove to me there's going to be enough
value and like there is another cohort
here that isn't just like 1 or 2% that
we're going to do a lot of work for
maybe not a lot of return. Hello, I'm
your host David Bernard. My guest today
is Michael Ribero, senior VP of global
consumer revenue at Condast, where he
helps oversee story brands like Vogue,
The New Yorker, GQ, and so many more.
This episode was recorded live on stage
at Revenue Cat's App Growth annual
conference.
On the podcast, I talk with Michael
about the blessing and curse of having a
brand, why post-purchase is a perfect
upsell moment, and why partnerships are
hard to pull off, but can be well worth
the effort.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> Yeah, [clears throat] I have really been
looking forward to this chat. So, you
and I got a a chance to chat a few times
ahead of this and um listen, you've been
on a lot of podcasts. If you want some
good listening, just search Michael
Rivero YouTube podcast and other things
like that. He's uh he's shared a lot of
insights over the years and so we're
going to pull some new things in, maybe
some old things in,
>> but it's going to be a really fun
conversation.
>> Thanks so much for joining me today.
So the the first thing I wanted to kick
off with is competition
and brand and you know we're in this
place in the industry where creating
apps to compete
is so much easier with AI and we're
seeing just a proliferation of apps. I
mean we were talking Jacob was talking
earlier about the insane increase we've
seen in the number of apps shipped. You
know, you have Instagram creators
sharing recipes competing with Bona
Petit. You have bloggers and influencers
and everything competing for MindSpace
with the New Yorker.
>> And there's like so much competition.
And then you were at the Washington Post
where like, you know, media has had a
decade of challenges with all the new
competitors and how to monetize and
everything like that. And so I thought
it'd be really interesting to start here
because I think a lot of the people in
this room and listening afterward will
be in a place where they're starting to
get a little worried like how do I
compete like you know what does brand
mean in this new age when you know Cali
spun up out of nowhere with 17y olds and
it's competing with my fitness pal and
lose it and you know some of these
storied brands in the app space are now
facing competition from like 17-year-old
kids. So I wanted to start there of like
how do you think about competition and
brand and and how to manage that?
>> Yeah. Um I'd probably offer maybe three
different things here. So brand I think
blessing and a curse. Um blessing in the
sense where you have this storied past.
I think the challenge was a lot of
brands especially in in media you
potentially get stuck in that past or
you essentially become your parents app
and like nobody wants to be their
parents app. maybe your parents, I don't
know, liquor or something else, but like
when you're your parents app or you're
your parents media outlet, I think that
could be a very difficult place to be.
So that I think that's the tension that
we ultimately work through. But, you
know, I think you you do have brand
recognition. You have consideration
because you've potentially be been
exposed to, you know, this brand since a
very young kid. I think, you know,
whether it's Washington Post or whether
it's, you know, MTV and a lot of these
different things, someone's exposure is
not necessarily like when they're
thinking about buying or ever going to
be a buyer. it's 10, 15, 20 years before
that and you know it's thinking how do
you ultimately nurture that tie over
time. Um, I know it's kind of backwards
and maybe not appropriate for an app
conversation, but I always refer to John
Deere if anybody has kids in the um in
the audience, but they make essentially
like a small little tractor. And you
know that kid is never going to probably
not going to be a buyer of a tractor for
40 or 50 years, but it's the early
positive association that you I think
you can um ultimately build on over
time. Um, the second is, you know, media
I think is very is interesting in the
sense everyone is maybe a friend of me
platforms and other brands. I think, you
know, it's nice with media in a lot of
times it's not a zero- sum game. So, you
can be a watcher or a reader of one
publication and usually that that's
actually a positive indication you're
going to read other things, right?
>> So, in a sense, we we fight, you know,
for real estate on the home screen or
the, you know, the app. But, you know,
in a way, you know, like there's always
that second position, third position.
The platforms is also an interesting one
just because it is this friendmy you
know it's fighting for now time like how
much time do you want to spend on the
office and you know historically for us
like Facebook was a great referer you
know all of these social platforms were
a great referer and now they're like we
don't want to refer you any traffic
[laughter] and it's a very difficult um
uh dynamic to deal with because you know
at the same time a lot of our readers
and our you know our current readers
people who want to ultimately subscribe
are on those platforms too and spend a
big chunk of time on on those platforms.
We really have to find ways to work
together. Easy to say, I think really
hard to do. Again, even cond is a really
small drop in the bucket for, you know,
someone like Meta. They say they care,
but I know they don't really care. And
so, we have to fight really hard in
order to, you know, how do we do
programming? How do we do paid media?
How do we do those various things? So, I
think, you know, between those two
things, it is really important. We
continue to invest in it. You know, the
one thing I think we were kind of
getting into backstage too is
potentially finding ways where you can
be different. Um yeah,
>> you know, the one for us I think has
really been how do you bring people
together in real life? I think community
is really important to people especially
now and you know in the context of AI
and all that jazz but we have this
platform I think we've used well and you
know I've seen it across my career where
you can bring people together in real
life help support that community and
then ultimately kind of feedback into
well you know how do you connect event
to event and it's really like being in
the app doing those sorts of things
spending time with us so you're ready
for that next event. that's been a way
we've able to see this as as a positive
cycle.
>> Yeah, I think the differentiation
is the key to a lot of this. And um it's
funny you brought up like the the friend
of me kind of thing. You probably don't
even know this, some of the audience
will. I run a weather app on the side
and I actually know that my target
market right now for my weather app is
weather nerds who probably have two or
three other weather apps on the space.
And so kind of the way you're thinking
about it as well, there are going to be
certain categories where it's okay like
embrace the competition like it's okay,
but how do you fight for that mind
share? Like how do you be the first one
they open instead of the second one they
open or the first one instead of the
third one that they open? How do you get
your widget on the home screen versus
like somebody else's widget? And and the
key there is that that the value prop.
It's like the differentiation is like
how do you think about that? And like
when you were at the Washington Post, I
mean, how did you think about
>> that in the world of just abundant free
media, you know, you were you were there
as you were transitioning into having to
charge more and payw walling more
things. Like how did you think about
that transition
>> and so much free competition and
creating that value?
>> Yeah, I think a little or maybe a lot
lucky and a little bit good on the lucky
front. I mean there are externalities
that I think when you find one of those
like take full advantage. Um you know
for us it was at the post it was the
Trump bump and then co and it's like
there's nothing I could have done to you
know to be a fraction of the success
that we saw because of those two things.
I think you know the good part is you
know when you do get that influx how do
you make the most of it? Um and then you
know what how are you taking the right
steps in order to set yourself up for
success. You know, one thing we thought
a lot about is how much access do we
give someone? Um, I think that was, you
know, really important. I think it could
have been easy to say lock it all. um
especially in those times and when
people would have paid weighing some of
these like short-term long-term benefits
also like you know the brand going back
to the brand consideration that um we
wanted to do right by people still be
you know successful from a business
perspective but just have that balance
of the amount we were harvesting now
versus like continuing to sustain and
feed for you know potentially success
down the road.
>> Yeah. How how did you think about the
that separation the free versus paid
because I mean this is like if anybody
in the audience and listening later
>> it is a really really tough thing to get
right like and and I know like watching
the post you all experimented with a few
different things right like do you give
one story do you give five stories like
how hard do you pay wall how many ads do
you use um what were some of those
internal conversation of like how how do
we
>> still be the story brand and and you
know a lot of folks they won't have that
kind of story brand, but they have to
make those similar decisions of like,
yeah, we don't want to make the free
experience crappy, but we want to
incentivize people. So, how did you
think about that?
>> Yeah, I um No good answer. Um [laughter]
>> it's a process.
>> No, definitely a process. I mean, I'd
maybe say three different ways to
approach it. You know, one, I think
always doing sort of a competitive
audit. You know, who's giving away what.
I think, you know, like we're talking
about before, I think people who are in
the category are going to be in the
category. The person who reads the post
is also probably reading the Times, is
also reading the journal. and you know
deciding you know do you want to be
different than your competitors and if
so like do you have a very deliberate
reason why and maybe it's certain
sections or certain features but I think
I think that's one um you know the
second is you've got to try stuff and I
think that's the easy part I think the
hard part is internally convincing
people to have this kind of test and
learn approach when you have revenue
targets if you're talking to a product
team and they really want to advocate
for one part of this should absolutely
be free because we want the most people
using it you know I think there's that
internal debate and you know ultimately
if you can align KPIs I think those
conversations become a lot easier. But
often like I would love a show of hands
of you know whose company's KPIs are
completely aligned so you can all make
perfect decisions. It's zero. I know
it's zero. So you know those two and
then you know lastly I think um just
willing to be wrong and maybe willing to
walk back. You know I think about us. We
put up a registration wall. We have a
property called Pitchfork. Um it's for
music fanatics. It's focused on music
reviews. We put up a regge wall
registration wall for certain folks. The
next day there was a big announcement on
the editorial side and the backlash that
we got of you're going to put up this
regge wall to now make us register when
it was completely free before and now
you're doing all these changes. I mean
it was it it was hard and so we just
took it all down and we said you know
what we're going to pause and we're
going to reset once we you know figure
out the editorial you know product part
of it right and then we'll you know
we'll try to remonetize it at that point
and I think I would say we're going back
through this process again of like is
now the time is now not the time and I
think we earn goodwill by be willing to
say hey you know we're going to walk
back on what we ultimately did.
>> Yeah that's a that's a tough you said
it's the easy part of like figuring it
out but but that's a hard part. I mean
especially like you know a big pitchfork
a brand with very loyal readers and very
loyal community Washington Post again
story brand I mean this is what I think
a lot of us struggle with like you know
my weather app is a hard payw wall and I
want to move it back to ad supported
premium tier but then what do you put
behind the payw wall what do you do and
I think there's always a hesitation of
and and so I love that you shared a
mistake
>> you should make mistakes like if you're
not making mistakes you're not trying
hard to like get that balance right. And
it's a great example of like you should
try and if you make a mistake, you can
recover and you can walk it back and
then take the next step. So yeah, if
you're operating a free app, if you're
if you've got a payw wall hard paywall
app,
>> try figure it out like and you need to
absolutely and I would say you know with
all the testing a lot of times you know
the person who I'd say is maybe you know
closest to the vision to the mission I I
would say is usually right. I think we
go back like so we recently launched
Vogue with an app. It was essentially we
relaunched the app you know before and
we were paywalling stuff which we hadn't
paywalled before. I think we had all of
these discussions what's the right way
to do it. Can we overlay AI to make
these decisions with us and ultimately
it was like you know I think it it helps
that it's Anna Winter and she's going to
have a very strong opinion too. But uh
you know like her gut was right. It was
like here's the most important stuff and
this is the stuff we should make people
pay for. So I think when you have a
partner like that, you know, whoever
might be in your organization, it's
really helpful cuz usually that's right.
>> That's and a win tour [laughter] being
your partner and figuring out your payw
wall. That's pretty cool. Well, the next
thing I wanted to talk about was, you
know, as a story brand, but as a print
publication that's like trying to enter
the modern age. I I've been impressed
with all the different kinds of
monetization experimentation that y'all
have been doing to figure out this new
age. And so, you know, I have a whole
list of of things that you've been
playing with, bundling, unbundling,
re-bundling, post-purchase, upsell. So,
let's walk through those one by one.
Yeah. And talk about and this is
something I think again this is um you
know, Tinder and and Dualingo and Cond
and some of these bigger brands have
started to figure these things out
>> that the rest of us will be figuring out
over the next few years. And so I want
to hear from you like how are you
increasing LTV with those p purchase
upgrades? How are you bundling? Let's
start with those and
>> yeah no absolutely I wish you know I
wish I could take credit for a lot of
this and it was a novel idea or not. You
know the one thing I would say is um I
always go back I think it was Picasa who
said the quote but good artists copy
great artists steal. I mean to me that
is I think I've based a lot of my career
on on that. I I mean on the bundling I
think you know part of it is what assets
do you have and how do you ultimately
put them together? You know you look at
something like the New York Times the
newspaper was deconstructed over years
and years and years with the internet
with you know various things and they're
essentially putting it all back together
making it really easy to buy. I think it
you know helps that you know they were
getting outside pressure to say like
make a bet on this. So I think that that
was a catalyst for a lot of our
conversations internally at Konda NAS.
we benefit from. We have this very wide
portfolio from GQ to Vogue. You know, I
go back to this double-edged sword is a
lot of times these things seem to fit
together, but sometimes they don't. Um,
you know, the question is, is someone
who is interested in architectural
digest also going to be the person who
is reading Wired? I think yes at points,
but you know, probably a lot of the time
no. Those are some of the considerations
we went into. What I will say, and I,
you know, I've now seen this work over
multiple instances, when you get to that
point of purchase, giving people more
for less money is always an equation
that's going to work. I um so like
coming from TV at one point in my life,
most people watch, and this was probably
five or six years ago, most people watch
something like six to eight channels. We
would try all sorts of messaging, all
sorts of packaging to say, hey, you
know, just get six to eight channels.
Every single test that we ran, it lost
when you said get over 100 channels. I
mean it was just it was unbelievable to
see. But I think you know reinforces
this the idea of like when you have that
moment of truth really making sure you
put your best foot forward even if it is
like it doesn't make sense or it doesn't
agree with any of the the research and
really the importance of testing. So
that's kind of where where we came from.
I think the one good thing too uh which
we're seeing now just on bundling is all
of a sudden you have different ways in
to a consumer. usually say with a single
subscription or if you don't pull it
apart it's hey it's one monolith there's
a benefit here and we're just going to
keep hammering that one benefit context
may not make sense there's something
might you know be external you know at
least for us and you know I'm sure a lot
of people who are doing the bundling is
you know here's another reason why we
can show you the value of the
subscription there's a new event coming
on there's a new tent poll that we could
talk about so that's been really um
interesting for us on the bundling front
>> yeah you know a lot of folks either
thinking well I don't have yeah
>> GQ vote and things to bundle. But when
you're at the Washington Post, you
bundled with Headspace. Tell me about
that deal cuz I This is another thing
where I think we're going to see the
subscription industry going [snorts]
>> is these kind of bundles like you know,
okay, you know, you're a huge outdoor
fan uh with All Trails and they have
some weather features in there, but can
they bundle all trails with the Weather
Channel to create this like synergistic
bundle between the two? And I'm just
throwing ideas out there, but like those
kind of things. And you did that at the
Washington Post. What did that look like
bundling with Headspace?
>> Yeah, I would go um you know two
different like so bundle internally. I I
do think there's a path bundling
internally. You have more assets than I
think you think you have. We recently
relaunched the wired subscription and
you know one thing that we were doing
but maybe not necessarily charging for
was AMAs with editors. And now all of a
sudden we said hey this is now part of
the subscription. We're only going to
make it subscription only. And so I
think there are things that either
you're doing that you can now put into a
subscription and call it a bundle or you
know probably low lift but maybe high
impact to kind of continue to build that
that existing offering you had. On the
partnership front I'll just warn like
buyer beware partnerships are really
hard.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Uh really hard and you know we did
multiple at um at the Washington Post
which I think is super exciting. You
know I think the theme we we really
tried to coales around one of two
things. One is like the occasion like
coffee and newspaper go together really
well. And so like we we hammered that a
whole in a in a bunch of different ways.
You can have access in you know certain
cafes or you know get a Washington Post
branded coffee bean with uh your
subscription. So that made sense and
then you know the other was really um
what person are you going after? That's
kind of more in line what you were
talking about. The context also helped
in the sense like a lot of the research
we got was people were just overwhelmed
by the news and so you know the insight
for us was yes we do some counter
programming shoulder programming that is
you know either happy news or you know
food or whatever it might be but like
realistically the post is going to be
known for very serious topics Washington
very serious stuff like so how do we
bring in this moment of maybe peace and
calm that was the thinking there um you
know I I would say trying to hammer out
a deal and really I think going in eyes
wide open is like are you going to be
the the big fish or the little fish? And
not to say like either position is bad
or maybe big spoon or little spoon. Um
but being okay with that going in I
think you know when you have two
companies that are kind of equal size or
at least in the same ballpark all of a
sudden it's like I want it on my stack
and I want control of the the building
relationship and all those things. You
know we've run into issues I've run into
issues before. So you know really being
deliberate about that. But if you can
make it work, I think very cool. Uh very
cool for the press and then you know
definitely business results behind it
too.
>> So what are what are you all working on
with post-purchase upsells? I know you
all made a lot of headway with those.
>> Yeah, I think this is if there's one
thing I always try to do like one do
this thing. Um I call it post
post-purchase upsell, but once you sell
your subscription either sell something
else, have someone else sell the real
estate to someone else so they can sell
something or ask someone to act, you
know, do some sort of action. that point
of purchase is probably the most engaged
your customer is ever going to be. You
know, we've taken advantage of that in
typically upselling another title or you
know upselling a premium type of
product. So you know for example if you
subscribe to architectural digest most
of the times we don't know in what realm
are you are you just a consumer who's
aspirational or is this your business so
we will offer kind of the business
membership after purchase and you know
we get pretty decent conversion rates in
that 5-ish% and all of a sudden you know
I have zero incremental customer
acquisition costs and you know now I'm
driving something like a hundred to $200
in lifetime value from just one pop-up.
>> Yeah. Um, it's
>> like give people an opportunity to spend
more
>> just Yes. And you know, you think about
>> and you know, any sort of purchase, but
like you know, car or McDonald's or
whatever it might be when the credit
card's out like you're ready to go, you
know, and so how do I just maybe put one
more thing in front of you? And again, I
don't need great conversion rates. I
just need little and I'm making a little
bit more money.
>> Yeah. I was talking to I don't know if
he's in the room, but uh Toby from
Bright Mind, this is a guy to talk to if
uh you're here in the audience or at the
conference. Um I was talking to him
earlier. He runs Bright Mind. It's a
mental health app, like kind of a a
meditation app. And I've known him for
gosh, like five years. We had an office
hours call together, and we were just
talking like 15 minutes ago about how,
you know, his app has done all right. Is
such a crowded space. It's so hard. And
so he recently introduced online
intensives, one-on-one coaching, monthly
4-hour meditation events, week-long
meditation retreats, and by taking the
thousands of subscribers, but then the
tens of thousands of engaged, you know,
email list and everything else like
that. He increased revenue 50% by just
thinking out of the box like, okay,
you're a subscription app, but like what
else can you sell? Like coffee beans and
the [laughter] and the the Washington
Post. So like I know a lot of this
sounds like oh he's at you know condass
and he was at Washington Post like you
can't do this. Toby's doing it like you
know he's thinking outside that box and
like increasing LTB and increasing
revenue by trying new stuff and like
engaging that audience. So props to you
and go find him. But that's exactly the
kind of stuff we're talking about and it
doesn't have to be at a global scale. It
can be in a smaller scale.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. I love it.
That's really great stuff. I think uh
lessons for everyone to learn. But I I I
do think you know knowing especially if
you just started an app I think those
are probably going to be your most loyal
loyal buyers and you know knowing that
the demand curve is not flat. It is
probably very steep especially for those
um those first buyers
>> but the willingness to pay curve like
we're not taking advantage of that. Uh,
absolutely. And I think, you know, we've
tried to do that and uh on a lot of
occasions, but you know, maybe doing
bespoke stuff that doesn't scale, but
you think is going to be worth it. I,
you know, I'm highly supportive.
>> Yeah. So, what do you mean by
unbundling? I'm I'm still a little
confused [laughter] that.
>> Um, essentially, you know, I think a lot
of like the push back that we've got is,
you know, from a media perspective is
this concept of um subscription fatigue.
And I think paired with the fact that
you know news and kind of I'm
overwhelmed with content. And so the
thinking was can you essentially create
a micro product or a mini product maybe
the diet coke to the coke and so when I
was at the post we did something called
a starter pack and as opposed to getting
an unlimited subscription it was
essentially three read four stories
every single month and then you know you
can decide you know you're going to if
you consume more you're going to hit
then another pay wall or kind of like an
upgrade wall and then go forward from
that. So that's the thinking
>> and that was like like two bucks a
month, right? Yeah. It's like way
undercut your main but how did that turn
out from an LTV perspective?
>> Um J still out. [laughter]
>> Well so I think you know there's two
things you know one the one thing I have
appreciated about publishing extremely
difficult to be in but you get a lot of
visitors and you get a lot of data and I
think like we ultimately decided that
this couldn't be a product that we were
going to advertise to everyone. It was
really in the cases where we saw low
propensity. We would determine
propensity really based on referral
source or you know something like that.
But if we could determine you were going
to be really low propensity. This would
be an offering and it would kind of be
but but really hidden kind of beside uh
behind the scenes but just trying to I
would say lower the hurdle to get you
into our payment ecosystem and then we
could go from there.
>> No, that's so smart. And I mean there's
so many ways to do that in an app. I
mean, I was talking to to Will from
WrestleM uh recently and we were talking
about like they they have some really
clever things they're thinking about
with being able to engage those people
who and you know it's pretty common in
the industry now of like you know people
are closing out the payw wall.
like, hey, they're there, so give them
an offer. Like, bring them in. But if
there's even, you know, even more smart,
even smarter, more sophisticated ways to
do that with data to figure out if
they're low propensity, like give them
that, but
>> don't give that to everybody. That's
great.
>> The last thing I wanted to talk about
was taring and how you think about
tiering. And again, I think like there's
just so much headroom
>> as a super app industry. We're still not
fully exploring the Tinders and
Dualingos are getting there, but
exploring the entire uh demand curve of
the people who just love your brand, who
are just willing to spend way more than
than your current offerings are. So, how
have you thought about breaking up those
tiers and being able to offer those like
really hardcore fans who are willing to
spend a lot more, let them spend? How do
you think about that?
>> Yeah. Um, I think really interesting
question. Um, I don't think anyone's
done it super well. I would say my
thinking on this has changed. Uh before
it was like let's just launch new
products you know um and new tiers you
know to that to capitalize on this very
dynamic. Some people are willing to pay
more than others. The adoption rates
I've seen have been low single
percentage and it's like well is it even
worth it? Um so you know I think I'm
more now I talk to the you know our
editors a lot and a lot of people want
to launch a premium product and I'm like
no I think that's a the status quo. I
was like, "No, but prove to me there's
going to be enough value and like there
is another cohort here that isn't just
like 1 or 2% that we're going to do a
lot of work for maybe not a lot of
return when we can be doing other things
like you know IRL or merch or whatever
it might be to sort of capitalize on
that same dynamic. So I think if you
have enough great it does feel you know
the examples out there whether it's ad
free or family okay I'm still not
completely sold on if that makes sense
like in the media world but we're
thinking about it. The one thing I would
call out is we we've gone more of the
away from the app but into kind of the
membership community world and you know
Vogue I think presents a really good
case study in trying to monetize
different parts of the demand curve or
the willingness to pay curve. We have
extremely high price products, very
elite select people. Everything IRL,
everything white glove to all the way
down to like, you know, premium in an
app, you know, making sure that your
your brand, your company, your product,
whatever it is, has like a large enough
umbrella. And if not, like really being
the default and no, don't do it. Focus
on driving as much subscription as value
into your subscription. Get the
retention rates right. the, you know,
the right pricing that you think uh
makes the most sense before you kind of
want to distract yourself because it is
distracting.
>> For a lot of companies, there is still
so much low hanging fruit. Don't jump to
the premium tier before you've captured
a lot of the lowhanging fruit. But you
can think more strategically of like
here's what we're wanting to build over
the next 5 years and here's how we're
going to build toward offering that much
value that we can charge more. So, it's
a fascinating place to play.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> All right. All right. Well, it's been so
much fun chatting with you. I wish we
could talk for another hour, but
>> thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
[music]
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.